so today I want to offer a book review
of what I think is one of the most
important books that I've ever read
philosophy in the flesh the embodied
mind and it's challenge to Western
thought by George Lakoff and Mark
Johnson this book is really powerful
because it does a critique of the last
2,000 years of philosophy through the
lens of contemporary cognitive science
so they take insights from linguistics
psychology neuroscience anthropology and
other related fields and then they go
back and reevaluate the foundations of
philosophy over the last two millennia
and one of the things that's really
powerful in this book is they introduce
a concept that they call empirically
responsible philosophy which basically
means that for a philosophical idea to
be legitimate it has to be consistent
with what we know from other domains of
knowledge but how the world actually
works and so they go through and look at
all the foundational concepts of
philosophy so causation time what it
means to be a person morality the
concepts for self and other such things
and they show that when we understand
how the human mind works in terms of our
natural embodiment meaning that the
kinds of minds we have are shaped by the
kinds of brains we have the kinds of
bodies we have and the kinds of social
and physical environments we find
ourselves in that when we take this
perspective which is now the established
scientifically valid way of
understanding the mind then we can go
back and critique the ways of thinking
that have been developed over the last
2,000 years and find the kind of do a
separation of the wheat from the chaff
showing which pieces are good and valid
and can still be kept and which ones
need to be updated or modified to
reflect what we now know and what I
really love about this book is that it
gives us a way of understanding what is
universally true about the human
condition meaning there are things about
the way our brains work in our bodies
the way that our bodies are structured
that are universal for all human beings
and how we can then use that as
dation from which to make sense of
what's happening in the world so one of
the big discoveries of social science in
the 20th century was that the
perspective that we take is always going
to have some level of subjectivity so
there's always going to be some bias or
incompleteness from any particular
viewpoint well that is a powerful
critique of the philosophical traditions
that assume it's possible to have a
universal what's called a bird's-eye
view to see how the world is outside of
a specific perspective turns out that
it's not possible to do that but there
are actually ways to take an approach to
building knowledge from within our
perspectives and then validate them by
critique and argument and debate among
other people who have slightly different
perspectives in order to get at what is
true and real and so this book answers
that question and results at once and
for all so when you hear people talk
about how there's this relativism and
that there are things that just can't be
known because we're always within a
subjective experience it's actually a
kind of a naive view of relativism it's
actually a more nuanced understanding
that lets us get back to what is real
outside of our own perspectives but we
can only get to it by going through our
perspectives and then comparing with the
perspectives of others around us and so
this approach to philosophy is developed
beautifully and powerfully in this book
philosophy in the flesh which I really I
can't recommend this highly enough it's
such a fantastic book for anyone who
wants to understand how to create
empirically responsible philosophies of
economics politics or other social
theories and then use them for design of
say urban environments economic policy
social policy and so on and so forth so
that's it I highly recommend this book
philosophy in the flesh by George Lakoff
in Mark Johnson enjoy